A code diff shows what an agent changed,
but not which layered instructions governed the run
or whether the session supports its validation claims.
Codex Rule Ledger turns those supplied artifacts into
an inspectable evidence ledger, always labeled as
an unattested local capture.
The demo reconstructs one launch-time chain from global
scope to the working directory.
This synthetic case includes global and project guidance,
a fallback, a deeper override,
and a candidate excluded by the byte limit.
It never invents missing history from today's filesystem.
Each observable instruction gets a source-linked state.
A successful test is supported.
A failed typecheck followed by completion
is contradicted by evidence.
A missing build event is not evidenced, not failed.
An untriggered documentation rule is not applicable,
and subjective prose is declined.
The inspector exposes the exact source and event anchors.
Export preserves every source, result, evidence link,
input hash, and warning.
The filename is bound to the
canonical SHA-256 ledger digest.
Those hashes bind supplied bytes after capture;
they do not authenticate the capture,
prove trusted time, or guarantee obedience.
Version zero point two adds a local CLI
for already-normalized Audit Bundles.
Recorded analysis is the keyless default and never
reads an API key.
This second synthetic case crosses the same deterministic
audit seam, produces six records across five outcome
classes, writes a private no-clobber file,
and proves the engine is not
hard-coded to one topology.
Codex independently selected this problem, scoped both releases,
and made the key architecture decision:
GPT should understand instruction semantics,
while deterministic code must own truth.
It implemented each vertical test-driven slice,
drove adversarial review repairs, deployed the keyless demo,
and packaged this submission.
Dan retained credentials, spend, eligibility, and publication authority.
GPT-5.6 maps complete instruction lines into source-linked observable
proposals; TypeScript owns discovery, hashes, evidence sufficiency,
and every final verdict.
Official feedback, metadata-only Langfuse, reviewed Git, green CI,
and production receipts corroborate that workflow without attesting
prompts, reasoning, or individual edits.
Codex Rule Ledger does not promise compliance.
It gives reviewers a compact,
runnable account of what supplied evidence supports,
what it contradicts, and what it cannot prove.